Previously on "The 100"...
They're murderers raising people
to give up their bodies.
We can wait 56 years for our baby girl,
or we can get her back tonight.
The mind of the host is erased.
The brain is left unharmed.
- Yeah. Yeah.
- Yeah?
The people from Earth,
how many of them are hosts?
We don't know.
That's what you're going to find out.
Echo made herself a
Nightblood in the lab,
same way Abby did to Clarke.
How many people have blood alteration?
Pass us the rope, and we'll
tell you what you want to know.
- What the hell is that?
- A temporal flare.
Come on. He's getting away.
In my dreams, I see a
Commander who frightens me.
Sheidheda, the Dark Commander.
That's why we must keep training.
Who are you?
Josephine Lightborne. Nice to meet you.
Have they convinced you that
we should leave paradise?
Why would I leave my home?
You're not Clarke.
How would you like to be immortal, too?
So Clarke was a Commander.
No. I told you,
she wasn't a Nightblood then.
Abby made me pump Ontari's heart
with my bare hands so
her brain wouldn't melt,
kind of gross.
Hmm, kind of badass if you ask me.
I didn't, but thank you.
Hey, I am offering you immortality,
a chance at godhood,
and you can't keep your eyes open?
Yeah. Well, even gods need to sleep.
Why don't you, by the way?
Sleeplessness is common
the first few nights in a new host.
You can sleep when you're dead,
which will be never unless
you've changed your mind.
- I haven't.
- Good.
Now wake up and show me
how to be Clarke enough
to fool her mother...
because no Nightblood, no drives.
Fine. Lightning round.
What card do you play when
Abby's on her high horse?
The dark year, cannibalism. Yum.
When you want to sprinkle on some shame?
- Addiction.
- Inspiration?
Uh, Clarke in Mount Weather,
Clarke in the City of Light,
Clarke staying behind so that
you guys could go to space,
which was fairly awesome, by the way.
Yeah, unless you got in her way.
OK. You've softened the ground.
She's ready to break.
Take the kill shot.
Daddy... executed for treason
and turned in by Abby herself.
Not bad. Maybe you do pull this off.
That would be Madi...
oh, you know, your kid.
Mm.
Consider it a dress rehearsal.
Fine.
Oh, uh-uh-uh. Easy, killer.
First, you get me past Abby,
and then I wipe my friends.
No, no, no.
You don't interrupt her when she's
communing with the Commanders,
not even Sheidheda, the Dark Commander.
He's getting too strong.
That's why we have to do
the separation ritual now.
I'm not letting her
suffer. Madi, wake up.
Hey, wake up.
Clarke?
Yep. That's right. I'm here.
It was just a nightmare, OK?
No. It was a memory.
- But it wasn't real.
- You know that's not true.
It is real for her,
and ripping her out can
permanently damage her.
But it didn't, did it, Madi?
You don't know what that just did
to her mind or to the Flame.
I'm fine, OK? I'm just tired.
Get some rest. We should go.
Yeah. You're right. You should.
Both of you.
Shut up. Let's start again.
Echo, Emori, Raven.
- Hey.
- It wasn't me.
Pull it together. It's show time.
Family meeting.
Where's Bellamy?
- Why? What's wrong?
- We ran into Jordan.
Is it true? They're immortal?
I'm sure he made it sound
worse than it really is.
They're murderers and body snatchers.
How much worse could it
be? We're out of here.
Hey, hey, slow down.
Where are we gonna go?
Murphy's right. The plan doesn't change.
We stay and learn as
much from them as we can
so we can build our own compound.
Bellamy's out scouting
a location as we speak.
He went without me?
This whole body-snatching
thing just really lit a fire.
He's out with a foraging party.
You guys were still with Ryker.
You let him go alone?
OK. Wait a second. Back up, Clarke.
You expect us to continue to play nice?
We do still need Ryker to tell us
how to bend the radiation field.
No. I'll figure it out myself.
Raven, I know this is hard,
but we've all done things that
we're not proud of to survive.
I haven't.
Fine. I'll try.
I'll go with her,
make sure she doesn't start a war.
I'm going after Bellamy.
Echo's going to be a problem.
I'll send Jade to keep an eye on her.
Yeah. Back to Bellamy,
there's no foraging party, is there?
Sure, there is, every morning.
He's just not on it.
See, he found out that I wasn't Clarke.
Swear to God, if you killed him...
I didn't, but I will if I have to.
You don't get it.
If Bellamy knows that Clarke is dead,
then all of this is for nothing.
He may was well just kill himself now.
That seems a tad impulsive.
I was thinking of giving
it till second moon.
That's when the
foraging party comes back
and Echo finds out I was lying.
You have until then to get him
on the side of the angels.
The angels being us?
We're all the hero of
our own story, John.
Come on. I'll take you to him.
Follow Echo.
Let me go!
What the hell are you doing?
Let me out!
Murphy.
Bellamy.
Heh. Oh, you figured it out, too, huh?
I bet that I can make
something to cut this strap.
- Who else knows?
- Nobody yet. Just us.
Tried to offer me a deal.
What deal?
We agree not to retaliate,
they help us build our compound.
And what did you say?
What do you think I said?
It's Clarke.
She might not have been
my favorite of late.
She's still one of ours.
She cared about you, Murphy.
I know that it may not
have always seemed like it,
but she did.
She cared about all of us,
and she would never let us die here.
You saying we should take the deal?
No. No. You were right.
We don't need them to help
us build our own compound.
We kill them all, and we take theirs.
Where's Blodreina when you need her?
Bioluminescence. Cool.
What if it's another trap?
You don't trap something
you think is already dead.
Quiet. On me.
Don't move. Don't make me shoot you.
Drop it.
Octavia, what is it? What's wrong? Move.
- Fascinating.
- Oh, it's spreading.
- What is this?
- I assume she went under,
leaving only her hand
exposed to temporal flare,
though not fully, or it'd
be fossilized like the trees.
I can help her,
not at the point of a gun.
Good choice.
There's medicine, but to get it,
we need to go back to the
place where it happened.
I'll give her 3 hours tops.
Before the time dilation
reaches her brain
and she's dead.
Fine, but then you're taking me
to the old man, or you're dead.
Ah, so you're looking for Gabriel.
What did Russell promise you?
40 vestal virgins and a side dish
of none of your damn business.
You're not boring. I give you that.
Channel the radiation through
a spatial light modulator
with a calculated phase variation.
And it follows a curved
trajectory in free space.
Cool. Got it.
We jury-rig the security pylons
Eligius used for the prisoners
- to handle the radiation.
- We provide the reactor fuel.
Yeah, out of the goodness
of your own hearts, I'm sure.
Did I miss something?
No. I did.
I think it's time to get some rest.
How long have you known?
No. You go. I don't need rest.
I need to get this done as fast as I can
so we get the hell out of here.
You know, as someone
who's lived with pain
for longer than I can remember,
I can get wanting a new body,
just wouldn't murder
someone else for it.
It's not murder. We don't force people.
Oh, yeah. That's right. I forgot.
You raise them from birth
to believe you're gods
so they sacrifice themselves willingly
for the greater glory of you.
It must be nice to be worshipped.
No, not really.
This you and your mom?
Priya, right? Hallowed be her name.
- Yeah.
- What's wrong?
I'm sure she's way more
important than some barmaid.
Of course, Delilah wasn't
just a barmaid, was she?
She was a daughter and a friend.
I was just a kid.
Russell killed us in the first red sun
not long after this was taken.
I didn't ask to be resurrected.
No, but...
you're Ryker the Ninth
now, though, right,
8 bodies?
How old were you when
you snatched this one?
206.
I'll look at that reactor now.
Item number one on our list...
red sun mushroom for
the adjustment protocol.
Oh, Josephine Prime's favorite ritual,
reason I miss her.
Be respectful. We're still
in the Offering Grove.
Who leaves to scout without a map?
Mercy.
I'll get you out of here.
Please. Mercy. They're inside me.
Stop! No.
You were in the tavern.
Why are you following me?
I have my orders. Let's go.
He's in pain.
Not that it's any of your business,
but he chose this path.
Jade...
You're strong. You can do this.
Join me.
I would, my friend,
but I have another charge.
You know him?
He's the guard who lowered the shield
that let your ship in
the night they took Rose.
He blames himself for her death.
He should blame me.
Now let's go.
- Mercy.
- I said no!
Hey, save your energy.
You're gonna need it.
Yeah? For what, another war?
Is that really what Clarke would want?
I don't know what Clarke would want.
It's too bad we can't ask her.
We know she wanted to do better.
Somehow I don't think
risking all of our lives
for revenge is a step
in the right direction.
Why aren't you restrained like me?
I don't know.
Maybe I seem less likely
to rip their heads off.
Why are you really here, Murphy?
You really want to know?
- Yeah.
- Fine.
I'm here to convince
you to take the deal.
There. I said it.
Why am I not surprised?
What did you see when you died, Murphy?
OK. I tried to save my own ass?
Yeah. I am,
but I'm also saving yours, just
like I did during the red sun.
Bellamy, if we take this deal,
we get everything we want.
We get to live.
Not Clarke.
We can't bring her back.
We can make sure the rest of us survive,
starting with you.
If you don't take this deal,
Josephine will kill you.
- Then let her try.
- Oh, so that's it, then?
We start another war? We
destroy another planet?
Is that what you want?
Is that what Monty would have wanted?
Hey, Monty... listen to me.
Monty would be ashamed of you.
Maybe he would be,
or maybe he'd see that
this is how we do better.
Get out.
Don't worry.
I'll do my best to make
sure they only kill you.
Wait. Tell me if I got this right.
The old man is actually
the original Gabriel,
Prime number 13, only he lost
his stomach for immortality,
so he became a terrorist
to kill his own people.
He'd call it a moral awakening.
Don't we all?
So you're looking for redemption...
is that it?
By helping Russell kill Gabriel.
I can offer you a better way.
No. Screw redemption.
Ah, I see.
Did Russell tell you your child
will be considered worthless?
You don't have the blood,
and neither will she.
They'll call her a null.
She won't be able to bear children.
She'll clean toilets or
volunteer to die as a
guard or attend to the dead.
- At least she'll be alive.
- If you could call it that.
Save your breath.
I'm not joining your little rebellion.
My days of fighting for
lost causes are over.
Really?
Then explain Octavia.
She's as lost as they
come, yet you help her.
Easy.
You know what I think?
I think you don't want her to end up
on the same page of your
history books as you.
You see a lot.
How is this possible?
That's a question for the old man.
Maybe he'll answer it
before you kill him.
Here it comes.
Tree sap? That's your miracle cure?
So help me God, if
you're just buying time
for your friends to come and save you...
"Buying time."
Interesting choice of words.
I prefer time in a bottle.
Leave me alone!
Heda.
I see him in mirrors.
Soon, he'll be everywhere.
That's why we need to do
the separation ritual now.
Where's Clarke?
I don't think we have
time to wait anymore, Heda.
You'll have to be strong without her.
Now, I've never done this before,
but, luckily, Raven kept Titus's book.
It contains the wisdom
of Bekka Pramheda.
The ritual is simple,
but you'll need to
focus like never before.
You won't be alone.
According to this, there's a dream space
in the Flame where you can summon
the other Commanders
to confront Sheidheda.
But if anything goes wrong,
you need to hold on to a good memory,
let it be like a shelter that
keeps you safe in a storm.
Do you have that memory?
The day I met Clarke,
before the bear trap.
Perfect.
Now lean back. Close your eyes.
Concentrate and repeat after me.
No. You're a liar.
Heda?
What is this? Let me go.
We're not through. The
ritual takes repetition.
The restraint is to protect
you in case he breaks through.
Let's start again.
Does Clarke know about this?
Clarke's not here. Now sit down.
Sound mind, sound body, sound heart.
Blessed be the Primes.
Any progress on the Kane problem?
"The Kane problem"?
Is that what you think this is?
No. No. There's no progress.
That's not what I meant.
What if I told you the Primes
had a way to save Kane...
But to do it,
you'd have to turn him
into a Nightblood first?
What are you talking about?
Come inside, and I'll show you.
They call it the miracle of sanctum.
All you need to do
is teach them how to make Nightblood,
and then that's yours...
well, Kane's, I mean.
You make him a Nightblood,
you download his mind.
That's it. It really is a miracle.
His mind is gonna go in
another person's body?
But we've done worse, haven't we...
the culling on the Ark,
Mount Weather, Becca's lab.
No. We did that to survive,
for all of us to survive.
And we did. We survived.
Now we get our humanity back.
By taking innocent lives?
Russell told me that his
people would volunteer for this.
If the Primes can make Nightblood,
then they can bring
back all of them at once.
It would be the most spectacular thing
that's ever happened here,
and people would love you for it.
That doesn't sound like you, Clarke.
I know.
I know. It's just...
Kane should be here, Mom,
more than the rest of us combined.
We've been trying to be the good guys,
but he's just good.
Yeah.
Yes. He is.
And this isn't just about you.
We need him more than ever.
If he could negotiate peace in Polis,
then he can save us here and now.
I wasn't aware that we needed saving.
We don't.
It's just a figure of speech.
Listen to me.
Mom,
I know you blame yourself
for Dad's death...
And I know you blame your addiction
for what happened to Kane.
Mom, I'm afraid of
what will happen to you
if you lose him, too.
And I can't lose you.
OK. I'll do it.
The Lees have been
part of our Prime family
for over 200 years.
How can we just erase them forever?
We don't really have a choice.
I've done my job.
Abby will show us how
to make Nightblood,
but only if we bring her lover back.
Why come to me, and not your father?
Dad thinks with is heart...
this body is proof of that...
but we have to be practical.
We have zero hosts,
so we either die in these bodies
or we wipe the Lees and live forever.
Mom, once Abby shows you
how to make Nightblood,
we'll never be on ice again.
The best part... no
more nulls, no oblation.
Anyone can be a host.
We'll have the genetic
pick of the litter.
Thank you for your sacrifice.
Mind turning that off?
Hey, don't touch that.
I'm trying to work. Turn it off.
My second host built that, Alejo,
made it when he was 12
out of recycled radios.
At least they were still
good for something, huh?
Yeah. An offering to the gods, huh?
How do you do that?
How do you make something
beautiful seem so profane?
News flash... keeping a gift
from somebody whose body you stole
is profane.
How about this?
This was given to my sixth host,
Tyman Averi, from his mother Annabel.
Every month, we celebrate
Ty's life together.
Is that profane?
So you haven't forgotten
the people who died for you.
- I'm touched.
- I think about them every day.
Hey, Abby needs you.
What for?
I don't know, something about Kane.
She needs to get up
to the mothership ASAP.
I'll relieve you here.
Have a nice flight.
Hey, can I ask you a question?
Is this your last body?
Yeah. Didn't think so.
Went to the spot we
chose for our settlement.
Bellamy wasn't there.
You already know that.
Where is he?
Please. Cut me loose.
The vines, I can feel
them under my skin.
Who sent you?
You said you had another charge.
I know what I said.
Clarke said Bellamy went to scout.
No one knew I was coming out
here except for my people.
The Primes knew she was a Nightblood.
Oh, my God...
that's not Clarke.
She's a Prime, and
you're protecting her.
I swear on my mother's soul,
if Bellamy is dead,
I'll slit your master's throat.
He's not dead, OK?
He has until second moon.
Thank you for being truthful.
I'll come back for you if I'm in time.
I don't want to fight, OK?
Why are you here?
Because we're both
struggling to live with this.
And I was hoping
maybe we could help
each other through it.
You went to my father?
I take big swings.
What are you doing?
Saving us.
He knows you killed Clarke.
And unlike the snake behind you,
he will cry over spilled milk.
Enough.
What the hell's the matter with you?
Have you become so callous
to the feeling of others
that you don't remember what it's like
to lose someone you love?
I know you're in pain.
I know you want revenge. I would too.
We had a chance to
bring back our daughter
and we took it.
We didn't consider the consequences.
- For God's sake...
- Be quiet.
Maybe you should just let the man speak.
- Shut up, Murphy.
I think you should hear him out.
I think we can trust him.
- Do you now?
- You can.
Look. I can't bring your friend back,
but I can guarantee safety
for the rest of your people.
We'll share everything we've learned
about surviving on this moon.
Why did our ship just take off?
Abby's showing them
how to make Nightblood.
I take it she doesn't know
that her daughter is dead.
You're gonna have to kill her, too.
You think my need for revenge is strong?
There's only one way this ends.
Bellamy, stop, all right?
You don't want them to
kill all of us. Just think.
Josephine!
Bellamy, come on. Don't do this.
I'm sorry, Daddy.
Violence is all they know.
If killing him is what you need,
then do it, but let
the violence end here...
An eye for an eye.
Big swings.
So what's the verdict?
The spreading seems to have slowed.
That's a good thing, right?
It's buying you some time.
I don't understand.
It sped up my healing.
Why is it slowing hers?
I supposed it's because
you don't heal old age,
but the truth is, I have no idea.
How long do I have?
Not long,
a day, maybe two.
You said it would cure her.
Actually, I said it might.
Whoa. What are you doing?
Cut it off.
Bold move. Will it work?
And if you say, "it might,"
we're gonna have a problem.
Hold on. Your arm's movement.
I...
I want to try something.
Here.
Let it scrape against the boulder.
Don't try to control your
hand. Just let it move.
Close your eyes.
That's enough. Take a look.
A logarithmic spiral,
the shape of the anomaly.
It's the source of the temporal flares.
I don't understand. What does it mean?
It's not just a tremor.
It's a message.
The anomaly's calling you...
just like it called me.
I guess we better see what
the hell this anomaly wants.
Bellamy...
what's going on?
Clarke's dead.
So when do we attack?
We don't.
We do what Clarke would have done.
We survive.
Madi, hey...
I have something to tell you.
I'm so sorry,
but training will help
you get through this.
Heda?
This is your fault.
- I know you're upset.
- "Upset"?
They killed her,
and now Bellamy says
we can't get revenge.
I understand why you might want that,
but if revenge leads to war...
No more lessons.
Heda, we can get through this together.
No.
As your Commander, you
are hereby banished.
Heda, think.
I'll have no choice but
to obey your command,
and you need my help now.
I said go...
now...
before I kill you.
Shut up.
♪ I ♪
♪ Don't belong ♪
♪ Slowly slip back
inside of my mind ♪
Clarke, I love you so much.
Mom?
I'm scared.
Clarke...
I'm afraid.
You don't have to do this without...
I will not let you die in this war.
Can we talk about something else?
We don't have to talk at all.
Synced and corrected by Octavia
- www.addic7ed.com -